Guide to the Philip Levy civil rights collection, 1948-1953
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections Research Center, George Mason University
Philip Levy civil rights collection
1948-1953
George Mason University. Special Collections Research Center.
Philip Levy
C0121
1 linear foot
This collection contains meeting minutes and grant proposals from the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) as well as correspondence on civil rights and race relations between senators and NAACP members. Many of the materials deal with the Fair Employment Practices Commission (FEPC), issued by Franklin Roosevelt in 1941 as executive order 8802.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Collection donor unknown.
Biographical Information
Philip Levy was a government official in several capacities, serving on the legal staff of the National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) and as counsel to Senator Robert F. Wagner. Levy practiced private law in Washington, D.C. during a career that spanned 1934-1970. He was directly involved with the development of national labor policy in the United States in the 1930s and 1940s, and maintained a continued interest in labor policy throughout his long career.
Scope and Content
This collection contains meeting minutes and grant proposals from the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) as well as correspondence on civil rights and race relations between senators and NAACP members. Many of the materials deal with the Fair Employment Practices Commission (FEPC), issued by Franklin Roosevelt in 1941 as executive order 8802 partly in response to protests organized by A. Philip Randolph. The bill was blocked from federal legislation by the conservative coalition in Congress, but five states passed their own FEPC bills: New York, New Jersey, Massachusetts, Connecticut and Washington. Several documents represented in this collection come from Connecticut.
The materials in this collection include a 1948 letter on civil rights from President Harry Truman to the Congress; a 1949 statement of Irving M. Engel on behalf of the American Jewish Committee to the House Committee on Labor and the Education Subcommittee on Discrimination in Employment; correspondence of Senator William Benton to Philip Levy, Walter White, and an op-ed to the New York Times; a 70 page "Program for Progress in Race Relations" submitted in 1951 by William H. Hastie, Arthur B. Spingarn, and Walter White on behalf of the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, Inc.; pamphlets from 1949 criticizing the Fair Employment Practices Commission on the bases of reverse discrimination and biological inequality between and among races; statements of Senator Herbert H. Lehman regarding civil rights, including an address to a Dinner of the American Civil Liberties Union; 1951 meeting minutes of the NAACP; and letters from the NAACP's Legal Defense and Education Fund to the Ford Foundation's Program Planning Division requesting support for research on unequal opportunities and world opinion on racial discrimination in the United States. The collection also includes various newsclippings and articles about race relations and civil rights during this time. Particular focus is paid to race relations in Washington, D.C.
Arrangement
Arranged by subject by Special Collections Research Center staff.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections Research Center also holds the
Index Terms
Persons:
Benton, William, 1900-1973.; Lehman, Herbert H.; Levy, Philip.; Weaver, Robert C.; White, Walter.
Corporate Names:
American Jewish Committee.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.; United States. Committee on Fair Employment Practice.
Subjects:
African Americans--Civil rights--History--20th century.
Contents List
- Senator William Benton Correspondence and Federal Fair Employment Practice Act (FEPA) Speech Documents, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Republican Party's Campaign Platform on Civil Rights, July-August 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Newspaper Clippings and Congressional Report on Closure/Cloture in Senate, August 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Civil Rights Legislation and FEPC Act in Connecticut Documents, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Connecticut State Inter-racial Commission-Highlights of the Annual Report", 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Congressional Record, June 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Statement of Irving M. Engel on Behalf of the American Jewish Committee To the House Committee on Labor and Education Subcommittee on Discrimination in Employment", May 25, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Fair Employment Practices Committee (FEPC) Notes, Correspondence, Report, and News Clippings, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- NAACP Committee Presentation to the Ford Foundation Documents, August 1950-December 1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Foreign Relations Documents, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Senator Herbert H. Lehman Addresses, Remarks, and Statements, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- NAACP Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Newsclippings on Segregation and Race, 1950-1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Handwritten Notes, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "The Poll-Tax Question", February 15, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "Preamble to the Proceedings of the Third Annual Conference on Civil Liberties", February 23-24, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Department of Defense Press Release-"Integration in Far East [Korea] to be Completed by Army", July 26, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "News from NAACP" Newsletters on "Major Candidates on Civil Rights" and "Records of Senators Sparkman, Nixon", July 31, September 11, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "A Program for Progress in Race Relations" by William H. Hastie, Arthur B. Spingarn, and Walter White Manuscript and Responses, May-June, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Factual Supplement to "A Program for Progress in Race Relations", 1951 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- "Proposals" by Dr. Robert C. Weaver - Proposal for Support of a Research Program on Hispanic Americans, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Proposed Civil Rights Projects and Handwritten Notes, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "Quizzing Nixon" - Interview with Then-Senator Nixon - U.S. News and World Report, August 29, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "Report on Korea: The Shameful Story of the Courts Martial on Negro Gis" Pamphlet by Thurgood Marshall, April 1951 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- "Segregation in Washington" Booklet, November 1948 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "Should Negros Back Sparkman?: A Debate" Article in "The New Leader", September 1, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- "Survey Graphic" Magazine-"Color-Unfinished Business of Democracy", November 1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Speech on Civil Rights, Possibly by Senator Benton, August-September 1952 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- President Truman's Message to Congress on Civil Rights, February 2, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- "Tentative Draft of Statement by Subcommittee Appointed at Breakfast Hill", circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- "Twenty Years of Civil Rights Progrress" by the Democratic National Committee, August 22, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Senator Robert F. Wagner Speeches, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Senator Walter White Correspondence and Articles on Civil Rights, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- "What the American Negro Wants" - Interview with Adam Clayton Powell, Jr. - U.S News and World Report, September 5, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Race Relations in Washington, D.C. Documents and Newsclippings, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- "The Washington Afro-American" Newspaper, January 18, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Reprint from American Journal of International Law - United States Congressional Peace Resolution, July 1920 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "American Diplomacy" by George F. Kennan, circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Martin Bursten and William Benton Correspondence, April 1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- U.S. News and World Report Articles, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- FEPA - "Speech of Senator William Benton of Connecticut in the Senate of the Unite States", May 9, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Universal Declaration of Human Rights, January 1949 (Box 2, Folder 7)